بذارید یه مقایسه بکنم، بین نرم‌افزارها و دستورات آشپزی
نرم‌افزار خیلی شبیه به دستور پخته. هر دوشون یک لیست از مراحل هستند که باید انجام بشن
همراه با قوانینی که مشخص می‌کنن این مراحل چه زمانی درست انجام شدن، یا نیاز به اصلاح دارن
و در نهایت به یک نتیجه مشخص ختم میشن.
اگه اهل آشپزی باشید، احتمالا بین دوستان‌تون دستورات پخت رد و بدل می‌کنید
و احتمالا اون‌ها رو تغییر هم می‌دید.
اگر از تغییرات خوشتون اومد، و همراه دوستان‌تون از غذای جدید لذت بردید
ممکنه که نسخه تغییر یافته دستور پخت رو به دوستان‌تون هم بدید.
حالا دنیایی رو تصور کنید که توش نمی‌تونید دستور پخت رو تغییر بدید
چون یک نفر تلاش کرده که این رو غیر ممکن کنه.
و تصور کنید که اگر دستور پخت رو به اشتراک بگذارید، دزد خطاب می‌شید
و تلاش می‌کنند برای سال‌ها زندانی‌تون بکنند.
من از کلمه «هکر» در مفهوم درست و اصیلش استفاده می‌کنم
برای توصیف شخصی که با شور و شوق هنری برنامه‌نویسی کامپیوتر رو دنبال می‌کنه
و همچنین شخصی که بخشی از فرهنگ هکرهاست، یا با این فرهنگ شناخته میشه
مثل اشخاصی که اینترنت، لینوکس و شبکه جهانی وب رو ساختن.
من فکر می‌کنم شما باید یک هکر باشید تا متوجه این طرز فکر خاص بشید
که در برابر این ایده که کد منبع سیستم‌عامل باید مخفی بمونه شورش می‌کنه.
این نگرش متن باز به راحتی با اقتصاد بازار آزاد کنار نیومد.
همچنین یک تهدید برای مفاهیم سنتی کپی‌رایت و انحصار فکری است.
کمپانی‌هایی مثل مایکروسافت که تجارت‌شون بر اساس کد بسته شکل گرفته
به‌طور فعال نرم‌افزار آزاد رو به شکل
یک هیولایی که مک‌کارتی‌گری (ویکی‌پدیا: جوزف مک کارتی) می‌کنه به تصویر می‌کشن.
همه این‌ها یکی از بزرگ‌ترین موفقیت‌های دهه ۱۹۹۰ رو رقم زد
که توسط رهبر با استعداد و گرانقدر این جامعه صورت خارجی گرفت
او دانه‌ای برای یک نهضت کاشت که شاخه‌های اون به گسترش‌شون ادامه میدن.
لینوس توروالدز یک سیستم کامپیوتری ساخت
که کل صنعت رو به شگفتی فرو برد.
لینوکس، یک سیستم عامل که الان روی ۸ میلیون کامپیوتر در دنیا اجرا میشه.
مجله وایرد: اون یک جادوگره که با واینامویمن برابری می‌کنه
و سیستم‌عامل اون، لینوکس، بزرگ‌ترین شاهکار اینترنت هست.
تصمیم توروالدز مبنی بر انتشار رایگان لینوکس
و منتشر کردن کد منبع لینوکس، از توروالدز یک شخصیت ستودنی ساخت.
لینوس تورالدز، نابغه کامپیوتری که رویاش مغلوب کردن مایکروسافت
و در واقع بیل گیتس هست. چطور پیش میره؟
افرادی هستند که میگن لینوس توروالدز دست پیدا کرده به یک
معجزه.
مورچه‌های کارگر به‌طور ثابت با یکدیگر به‌وسیله مودم در ارتباط هستند
کد رو منتشر می‌کنند، مشتاق بازخورد تغییرات هستند
برای ساختن بهترین سیستم‌عامل ممکن در دنیا.
سن ژوزه، کالیفرنیا
من نمی‌خوام هیچکس دیگه‌ای همین مسیر که من رفتم رو دوباره طی کنه
برای پیدا کردن چیزی مثل لینوکس. شاید یک دانشجوی کامپیوتر دیگه
سیستم‌عامل خودش رو لازم داشته باشه و اون مجبور نیست از اول شروع کنه.
این یک جنگ علیه آسیاب‌های بادی نبود.
این، دون کیشوت در برابر دنیا نبود
در تلاش برای ساختن یک مکان بهتر.
بیا، بیا. غذا می‌خوای؟
من بیشتر ترجیح میدم با دیگران به‌وسیله ایمیل کار کنم تا رو در رو.
در غیر این‌صورت شما وارد همه این بحث‌ها و جزئیات مهمل میشید.
روی ایمیل، شما باید قبل از ارسال یک پاسخ کمی فکر کنید.
فقط به‌خاطر این‌که ما توی یک مکان نیستیم، معنی‌ش این نیست که
ما درکنار هم یک اجتماع نیستیم. این مثل یک دفتر کار مشترک خیلی خیلی بزرگه.
ما حتی بحث‌هامون رو هم در اینترنت انجام می‌دیم.
این یک پروژه عظیمه. من هیچ پروژه نرم‌افزاری نمی‌شناسم
که افراد خیلی زیادی از مکان‌های مختلف روش کار کرده باشند
که همه این‌ها رو کنار هم قرار بدن.
مهم‌ترین خلاقیت جامعه لینوکس، کد منبع نیست
بلکه اجتماعی است که حول آن شکل گرفته.
لینوکس چیه...؟ بذارید این‌طوری بگم...
همه کامپیوترها متفاوت هستن، همه فلاپی‌خوان‌ها متفاوت هستند
همه هارد دیسک ها متفاوت هستند، همه پردازشگرهای گرافیکی متفاوت هستند...
لینوکس اون چیزیه که می‌دونه چطور باعث بشه همه این اجزاء مختلف
وظایف ساده رو انجام بدن. مثل «فایل من رو بریز روی دیسک» یا
«این فایل رو از این فلاپی که من دارم بخون»یا «این عکس رو روی صفحه ترسیم کن».
لینوکس می‌دونه چطور با این اجزاء مختلف سخت‌افزاری صحبت کنه
تا اون‌ها عملیات‌هایی که ما از کامپیوتر انتظار داریم رو انجام بدن.
وقتی که می‌گیم «لینوکس» منظور ما چیه؟
بعضی‌ها منظورشون کل سیستم‌عامله
یعنی هر چیزی که در کامپیوتر اتفاق میافته.
بعضی‌ها می‌گن «لینوکس»، برای اشاره به مهم‌ترین نرم‌افزار؛ هسته.
این برمی‌گرده به شخصی که این بحث رو شروع کرد. به شخصی که
یک جوری از اینترنت برای ساخت یک اجتماع از افراد استفاده کرد
که حس می‌کردند همه همکاری‌هاشون ارزشمنده.
That ability to foster cooperation
could very well be something-
-that can only come from a
person raised in a country like Finland.
Helsinki, Finland
1969 - it seems to
have been such a good year.
The moon landing, Woodstock, the birth
of ARPANET, that led to Internet.
The first steps of UNIX, the
operating system for big computers-
-and on December 28
Linus Torvalds is born.
All children learn primarily
through playing.
For that reason I think it was
very important for Linus to enter-
-the computer world when computers
still were simple enough even for a-
-10-12 year old boy to understand
what was inside this machine.
In today's world there's so
many layers of information and-
-complicated stuff between that which
is shown on the computer screen-
-and that which is inside the machine.
It's difficult for the children of today-
-to play their way to the insight
the same way Linus did.
I think it was love at first
sight both for my father and for-
-Linus who together were childishly
excited, both of them, to try-
-the possibilities that VIC-20 offered.
The place where Linus developed
Linux is no longer-
-because the walls have
been torn down.
Here in the corner where the couch is
is where Linus' desktop and computer,-
-that he worked on, used to be.
The biggest change is that he
nowadays is a stand up-guru-
-because he is used to perform in front
of an audience and he can handle them.
That might not be surprising, but still
striking when compared with how-
-he actually was: relatively shy and
withdrawn, and not the one who-
-got in touch, but his friends were
the ones who kept in touch with him.
Hello everybody out there using MINIX.
I'm doing a free operating system.
Just a hobby. Won't be big
and professional-
-like "GNU" for 386 and 486
AT clones.
This has been brewing since
April and is starting to get ready.
I'd like any feedback on things
people like or dislike in MINIX-
-as my OS resembles it somewhat.
Any suggestions are welcome-
-but I won't promise I'll actually
implement them.
torvalds@kruuna.helsinki.fi
1991 - The Soviet Union closes down.
The Gulf War.
The British physicist
Tim Berners-Lee-
-releases a hypertext system,
calling it the "World Wide Web".
Microsoft is well on the way
for world domination.
And on September 17
Linus Torvalds sends the first-
-version of Linux, 0.01,
to the world, via Internet.
The first responses arrive
within hours.
"Linux was invented here"
"University of Helsinki"
We first heard whispers
in the cafeteria-
An operating system was being
developed and started to spread.
We learned to know Linus better.
His programming skills had
already been noted here.
Linus based Linux on UNIX,
because of its basic ideals.
The original UNIX operating system
had been created by Ken Thompson-
-and Dennis Ritchie
at AT&T's Bell Labs in 1969.
UNIX was in the beginning a
relatively free operating system-
-and very popular in
the university circles.
The philosophy is
based on two notions:
Firstly, everything is a file.
Secondly, when you build something
you write things that are for a single-
-purpose but to
do that purpose well.
Putting Linux on the net
was kind of natural in many ways.
There were a lot of small reasons.
Like the fact that I thought it was-
-a good idea to make Linux available to
others so that they could try it out-
-and send comments back to me.
He really had two choices.
He could make it completely free-
-or he can try and charge for it.
Linux would not exist if he
had tried to make profit out of it.
Nobody would have bought it.
It would have been a dead end.
You haven't been here for a while.
We've already installed the third version...
We had difficulties to fit
Linux-stuff into one computer.
At first Linus didn't want to
release Linux for free.
He was thinking hard about
what kind of copyright he would use.
I persuaded him to release it
under the GNU copyright.
Especially, as the compiler I
used was released under the GPL-
-I eventually ended
up using the GPL myself.
The "GNU General Public License" (GPL)
funded by the Free Software Foundation-
-in the mid 1980's says that
if you change and modify the code-
-you have to make your changes
and improvements freely available.
The GPL hinders any one person
to have a monopoly-
-over an important
piece of technology.
I think the timing was good. Even
just a year earlier I don't think it-
-could've been done, and a year later
someone would've done something similar.
The Internet hadn't gotten
to the general population-
-but it was getting very strong
in university networks.
I'd done a mailing list program
in the "C" programming language-
I had to expand it
and add features.
Rapidly thousands of
people were interested.
It was a surprise. The numbers
doubled in short intervals.
It was crazy. After 1000 people
2000, the next day 4000 people.
Without Internet Linux development
would've been like chess by mail.
My name of choice was "FREAX".
Which was both "free", "freak"
plus the "X" that you need for UNIX.
I didn't like the name FREAX.
It wasn't very commercial...
Ari Lemmke, who actually put Linux up for
FTP, thought that it really was a bad idea.
He really hated the name. He
made the FTP site available and just-
-called it Linux because
that was the working name.
The name stuck, and Linux
is a much better name...
"GEEKS"
"NERDS"
We have an impressive
set of geeks and nerds here.
The first question from the easy category:
"How do you pronounce Linux?"
Well, I pronounce Linux as "Linux".
However, the total answer
to that is if you're Linus Torvalds-
-you probably pronounce
it "Leenux". On the other hand,-
-if you come from the west
coast of the United States-
-you pronounce it as "Lynix". And Linus
said he doesn't care how you pronounce it-
-as long as you just use it!
It was in July of 1991-
-which was shortly after Linus had
released the 0.09 version of the kernel-
-that I started playing with Linux.
Heard about it on, I think, Usenet.
Downloaded it from Finland,
started playing with it-
-and thought it was really neat!
At that point there was very
limited trans-Atlantic Internet bandwidth-
-so it was very painful to down-
load all these packages from Finland.
And so I decided: "Well, we
need to do something about this"-
-and I used my personal workstation,
"TSX-11.mit.edu"-
-and I set up a mirror archive of all the
kernel sources on my private workstation.
And that was the first US
Linux FTP site that came into existence.
The first time I got Linux was I
downloaded the floppy images for Linux-
-and in the Penn State University computer lab
I installed it on one of their machines.
They subsequently kicked me
out of the computer lab that day-
-but that was my
first experience with Linux.
Very early in 1992 suddenly
I didn't know everybody anymore.
That it was no longer
me and a couple of friends.
It was me and a couple of
hundred people who I had no idea-
-where they were, what they
did with the system, and who they are.
And that was a big step.
University of Helsinki
The 1.0 release in 1994 was certainly
important and it meant a lot to me-
خب چون کلی کار پشتش صورت گرفته
آن حقیقتا واقعه‌ای بود برای کاربرد تجاری لینوکس.
حقیقتا استفاده تجاری قبل از لینوکس ۱.۰ سخت بود.
به کنفرانس خبری سیستم‌عامل لینوکس ۱.۰ خوش آمدید.
چرا این هست نوعی از سیستم شبه یونیکس ساخته شده.
مخصوص دانشگاه هیلسینکی ؟
چون اونجا برای pc سیستم عامل یونیکس وجود داشت.
اما آنها خیلی گرون هستند.
برای مثال داس قیمتی حدود ۲۰۰ مارک دارد.
قیمت یونیکس ۲۰۰۰۰ مارک است.
این برای یک دانشجو خیلی زیاده تا پرداختش کند.
می‌توانید به یک فروشگاه کامپیوتر رفته و سوال کنید.
آنها به شما شبیه کسیکه دیوانه است نگاه می‌کنند.
در واقع، این اسونه که خودتون بنویسید.
فرایند توسعه لینوکس، یگانه است.
رتبه‌بندی ندارد ولی هرکسی آزاد است تا پیشنهاد تغیر کد بدهد.
یکشخص رهبر است و تصمیمات بزرگ می‌گیرد و بهترین ایده‌ها رو انتخاب می‌کند.
لینوس « دیکتاتور نیک‌سرشت »
همه می‌دانند باید کسی سرپرست این کارگروهی باشد.
و طبیعی که لینوس سرپرست باشد، چون هسته کرنل لینوکس را ساخته.
و لینوس شخصی است که خیلی خیلی رهبر خوبی است.
او در واقع شخصی است بسیار فروتن.
او حتی سعی نکرد تا اعتبار و اسمی برای کاری که کرده بدست آورد.
شما می‌خواهید داشته باشید صدها، هزاران شخصی که کار می‌کنند روی کرنل
در بعضی زمان‌ها.اما نمی‌توانید از همه این اشخاص بخواهید...
یه ضرب روش باشند. هر شخصی در اوقاتی بهش رسیدگی می‌کنه
چون مسیری است تا برای حل شکلات باید سپری کند.
تضاد بین شما و دیگران می‌تواند باعث وقوع یک درگیری در اون زمان بشه.
من فکری را بکار میبرم تا سلسله مراتبی باشد که من سر باشم
و انها افسران من
و من فکر نمی‌کنم راه دیگری باشد، شبیه به یک اعتماد در وب می‌ماند.
-where I have people I trust,
and they have people they trust.
Well, there are lots of things
that motivate developers!
There's artistic pride, the satisfaction that
you get from doing good craftsman-like-
-work. There's the
idealist feeling of being part of-
-something larger
and more important than you are.
There's a desire to help
the world and see that solutions happen.
In the absence of monetary rewards
most people, most of the time,-
-are playing for a kind of
reputation reward among their peers.
One strength of
the Linux development world-
-is that practically every software
author can be contacted directly by email.
Ted Ts'o was crucial in
the spread of Linux in the United States.
To be fair, it's very easy to say:
"If we were in charge
we wouldn't do these things".
But then again, we're not getting
all these email messages saying:
"Please, let me add this new feature!"
So I don't know what I would
actually do if I were really in charge.
Dave Miller is a
maintainer who reviews changes-
-that developers
want to make in the kernel.
He is like a funnel between
the contributors and "the king" Linus.
The way that we work is...
You can talk all day about a great idea-
-or a solution
to a problem, or something that-
-you think is an interesting feature
for Linux to have but you gotta-
-show us something concrete.
Show me a piece of code that does that.
Something that's tangible that I can
test myself so I can try it out and I can-
-think about what it is. Instead of just
talking abstractly about a topic all day.
Alan Cox, a "renaissance hacker"
is the closest collaborator to Linus.
His right hand man.
"What is Alan doing...
The other side of the story"
To me code has more in common
with i.e. poetry or some kinds of writing.
The beauty of it is in the structure,
in putting ideas across one at a time-
-in a clear way.
So a good piece of code you read
without comments and it's immediately-
-obvious why it's been written, how
it's elegant. So you're looking for code-
-which is both clean and elegant. But also
doesn't rely on clever programming tricks,-
-doesn't make assumptions
which may not be true in the future.
Because the last thing we want to do
is having much code in the Linux kernel-
-which requires large
amounts of effort to keep it working.
We want code which will just
continue to work, and work forever.
Having led the Linux project
for five years in Helsinki-
-Linus was recruited to
Silicon Valley, California.
He wanted to see the other side
of the world, the world of commerce,-
-not just the academic side.
"Edward Helmore talks to Linus Torvalds,
Silicon Valley's brightest new star"
You're quite an un-orthodox figure in
the Silicon Valley world.
What do they make of you there?
You're not taking their
crazy commercial part, if you like.
"TRANSMETA"
Linus started to work for
a company called "Transmeta"-
A little Linux company,
but a mysterious business-
-that didn't want to tell,
for many years, what it was up to.
و به صورت متناقضی یک کمپانی کلوز سورس بود..
قراردادی که باعث میشد لینوس هم چنان بر روی توسعه لینوکس تمرکز داشته باشه.
I have been forced into trying
to be a poster boy for Linux-
-and actually the whole
open source community at large,-
-even though I wasn't even
the person who started open source.
شخص واحدی نماینده کل داستان نیست
و نقطه شروع یکتایی وجود نداره.منظورم اینه،این شبیه بامبو هستش:
شما نمی دونید چه جایی شروع شده و کجا به پایان میرسه.
فک نمیکنم این انقلاب تماما یه حرکت جدید هست.
مدت زمان زیادی وجود داشته در اطراف ما
حتی در دهه 70 میلادی،تمامی نگرش ها پیرامون یونیکس
با اینکه از دید تکنیکی متن باز و آزاد نبود
چون شما نیاز به تهیه لایسنس از AT&T داشتید.
Since that was not an issue
generally, you could share things freely.
When you run a program, typically
you run the executable form-
-which is a series of numbers and
nobody can make any sense of them.
Only a computer can understand them.
That's what they're for.
Those numbers are the form of a program
that the computer can understand.
For humans to figure out what they
mean is very hard. When we write software-
-we write it as source code, and it
looks sort of like algebra. That's the form-
-that you can
understand if you're a programmer.
To help you figure out there
are usually lots and lots of comments-
-which are explanations that are put into
the source code to help other people-
-figure out why the
program is written the way it is.
If you get just the executables, which is
what Microsoft will probably give you-
-even if you had the freedom to make
changes you could never figure out-
-what changes to make.
It's too hard!
For the freedom to change the
software to be practical, and usable,-
-you gotta have the source code.
If you really look at the project...
As I said, Linus developed the kernel-
-but I think that the most
interesting part here is really-
-Richard Stallman began the movement.
Have you heard
of Richard Stallman?
He wanted everyone to have the rights
to use the software, to copy the software-
-without breaking any laws.
To make changes, distribute them,-
-enhance the software. He wanted to
give people rights!
When he decided to overthrow corrupt
American capitalism in the IT industry-
-he quit his job
and continued coding.
Join us now
and share the software
MIT,
Camebridge, Massachusetts
You'll be free,
hackers, you'll be free
I tend to think of things in terms
of justice, freedom and ethics.
I announced the idea
in November 1983-
-but it was in Januari 1984
that I quit my job at MIT-
-to start developing
a free operating system-
-to which I gave
the name "GNU".
This is "GNU General Public License"
and of course the kernel is under GPL...
"Free software", I should explain,
refers to freedom, not price.
It's unfortunate that the word "free",
in english, is ambiguous-
-it has a number
of different meanings.
One of them means "zero price",
but another meaning is "freedom".
So think of "free speech",
not "free beer".
There's a similarity between
the folk process where a poem-
-or a song or a story
can get refined and reshaped-
-by one teller or singer
after another-
-and the way
free software gets improved.
You'll often find cases where a free
program is being developed now by-
-a group of people who
include none of the original developers.
In 1991 we had almost finished
the GNU system.
Our goal was to make an OS, like
UNIX, but entirely free software.
This complete operating system
required many different components-
By 1991 we had
almost all of those components.
Many of them we had written,
and many others we had found-
-somebody else had written it for
his own purposes but it did the job.
And so we pressed it
into service as a part of GNU.
One major component was still missing:
the component called the "kernel".
So it was very useful
that Linus Torvalds wrote a kernel.
At that point, combining his kernel,
Linux, with the larger GNU system-
-produced a complete
runnable system that-
-you could actually
put onto your PC and run.
So once Linux was developed
the GNU system in effect was completed!
It began to catch on in
popularity, but at the same time-
-an unfortunate thing happened.
The people who were using-
-the GNU system didn't
realize it was the GNU system.
So they began calling the
whole combination "Linux"-
-and that confusion spread.
As a result, it's very hard
for us in the GNU project-
-to call the user's attention
to the ethical and political issues.
Hoarders can
get piles of money
That is true, hackers,
that is true
But they cannot
help their neighbor
That's not good, hackers,
that's not good
Most computer science in the USA comes
traditionally from military background-
-and defense spending.
Perhaps it isn't any more quirky that
nowadays the "free software" movement-
-finds room both for
Richard Stallman and libertarian ideals.
Many saw free software also
as a new way of making money-
-and needed a less radical concept.
Enter: open source.
"I want you to be an
open source developer"
We looked at the history
of advocacy in what at the time was-
-still mostly called the "free software"
movement and we concluded-
-that it hadn't worked!
That in fact the rhetoric and the tactics
used by Richard Stallman and the-
-Free Software Foundation had left us
worse off than we were when we started.
The term "open source" doesn't
really imply the political issues-
-like it used to and the
"free software" term still does.
There's now a second movement,
the "open source" movement-
-where they consider
only the practical benefits.
They refuse, and I mean
that literally... they carefully avoid-
-the issues of principle, freedom, ethics
and making a good society to live in.
That kind of language is
implicitly threatening to people-
-whose day-to-day concerns are: "how
do I increase my shareholder value?",-
-"how do I keep
control over my business?"
How do I address my
actual down-to-earth problems?
When you walk into their offices and say
"you should use all open source for your-
-business because sharing is good
and hoarding is evil" - it doesn't work!
I am not against business.
I don't believe in abolishing business.
I do business myself. But I believe
business should not dominate all of life.
The rules of society should not
be chosen primarily to please business.
Early in 1998 the majority usage in
the community went from "free software"-
-to "open source" in six weeks flat.
In the late spring or early summer of 1998.
That told me that there had been huge
pent-up demand in the community-
-for a way of explaining what we
were doing that was more effective.
The whole attitude in the
trade press and the investor community-
-completely turned around!
The same people who had spent years
sneering dismissively at "free software"-
-and talking about
sandal-wearing freaks with long hair...
Those very same people within a year
were falling all over themselves to write-
-laudatory articles about the wonders
of open source and peer review.
-and this is really funny
because it was the same software-
-and in most
cases the same people!
"Robin Hood of the nerds"
"Martin Luther, meet Linus Torvalds"
Linux happened without
the help of people with deep pockets-
-or even despite the help.
How can we keep from destroying the
magic by pouring all this money into Linux?
When Linux started
to become commercialized-
-people said: "oh well, we'd like to
keep it as our own little project".
"Nobody should be
making any money off it".
Well, in the real world people make
money off things. The US is a capitalistic-
-society and
Europe is a capitalistic society.
In order for
companies to start using Linux-
-they wanna have somebody sitting
there, who can give them support,-
-who can sell them the hardware.
And these people who sell this hardware
and support are going to make money.
Not everyone
of us is a hacker.
Actually, very few of us would take the
effort to download Linux from the net.
Even fewer will tackle with the
code itself in order to improve it.
Though, Linux was
hard to use, customers valued strongly-
-its reliability
and open source code.
There was an opportunity
for companies with new visions.
"Red Hat"
For Red Hat, it wasn't
important that we ship a better-
-operating system than
Microsoft's or Sun Microsystems'-
It becomes really important
that we ship an operating system-
-that solves a problem for our
customers that they cannot solve-
-using the traditional
proprietary "binary only" software.
We were recognizing
what we were doing was we were-
-building technology
and then giving it away!
So we said: "Well, how do
you make money doing this?"
Of course, we would go to California,
to Silicon Valley, and everyone said:
"Well, you cannot make
money in the software business-
-by giving your technology away".
We would come back and talk to our
customers and we realized the only thing-
-that kept our customers loyal
was that we did give away our technology.
For the very first time they had control
over the technology they're using.
The real value in most software products
is the active maintainence down the line-
-the continuing support
relationship between the vendor and you.
That's what gives software
fundamentally the characteristics of-
-the service industry rather
than the manufacturing industry.
Linux is flourishing in the
Internet server appliance area.
But because there has not been an
easy-to-use software for home users-
-it has only a small
margin of the desktop market.
The GNOME project, with its
graphical interface tries to fill that gap.
But hacker elitism
still seems to follow Linux.
Do you see who's here?
It's a penguin!
-It's Tux, actually...
-Hi, Tux!
When Linus Torvalds makes
millionaires and billionaires-
Bill Gates' hair turns grey...
Microsoft has a very traditional model:
They make closed source code,
they put it on a CD, they sell that.
They take on all the
burden of development themselves.
Everything goes back through them.
Once you're in that business
it's very hard to change your culture.
It's very hard to change your business
to one where you cooperate.
It's easier to make money
off closed source products-
-if you don't need, or
you have the huge market share.
So, for example, Microsoft
does not have a huge incentive-
-to open source
their code right now.
And it would probably cut
into their profits, so I don't think-
-they're gonna do it,
or at least not willingly.
There's algorithms that you
may in fact want to keep proprietary.
For example, I know of certain
compression algorithms that companies-
-have put a lot of work into.
For things like streaming media.
And they don't want people
to know how they do that -
-because it's exactly how they
do that that's the value of the product.
Fighting between Linus,
who's the leader of Linux, and-
-Bill Gates who's the leader of Microsoft.
It becomes
really personal.
Next, for our bizarre question:
"Whose lips are these?"
As an answer:
Bill Gates' lips telling another lie...
The acceptance of Linux has
been helped enormously by the fact-
-that people have known that
Linux exists through the news.
The "David versus Goliath" story helped
there, but I don't think it's particularly true.
"Microsoft's Ballmer
claims Linux is communism"
-You are a socialist...?
-That's one of the labels
that people put on me.
-Is that true?
It's not a secret that I was a
left wing radical in the late 1960's.
Students' UN organization was
behind most demonstrations.
My personal belief system is
more one of personal honour.
I don't care what anybody else does...
I want to do what I feel is right.
Linus keeps a very strict
distance to politics.
I think he suffered slightly
in his earliest childhood-
-as his father was so active politically.
It is also about
having a social conscience-
-and if you call that socialism
then, yeah, I guess I'm socialist...
He is radical within a very restricted
area, where he sets the limits himself.
He is very reluctant
to take part in fuzzy political discourse-
-and there's the difference
between the pragmatist-
-who wants to work with concrete
stuff and not let the steam-
-go out through his ears,
like we used to do in the 1960's.
This is a community. You can take
but you must give back!
-من بسیار خوشبختم ازینکه امروز اعلام کنم
-برنده امسال جایزه IDG لینوس توروالدز : دبیان است
-این بسیار خوبه که لینوکس به سمت چیزهای جدید نظر مثبتی نشون میده
-شامل جنبه های تجاری می‌شود.
-سلام، من از برزیل اومدم و بسیار مشتاقم بدونم چه کارهایی میتونیم انجام بدیم
-برای آوردن شما به برزیل در ماه می سال بعد؟
-آیا شما به مهمانیVA در شب چهارشنبه می‌آیید؟
-من به احتمال زیاد خواهم آمد اما در حال حاضر باید بروم...
-من شنیده‌ام که شما به تیراندازی می‌روید؟
-تو با ما می‌آیی رفیق!
-نــــــه...
بسیاری از جوامع نگران این شرکت‌های بزرگ هستند, این فروشندگان تجاری بزرگ
-به سمتی نمی‌روند که توانایی برگشت به جامعه را داشته باشند
-این چیزیست که مردم انتظار دارند دیگران به خوبی مراقب همه چیز باشند
-و من فکر نمی‌کنم این درست باشه,
-و فکر هم نمی‌کنم که باید درست باشه
-و من فکر می‌کنم قدرت لینوکس  پابرجاست حتی اگر کسی به شما کمک نکند
-و در هر اینچ (واحد اندازه گیری طول) از مسیر,
-شما هم‌چنان یک کپی از لینوکس خود را دارید
-و شما هنوز این قدرت را دارید که هرکاری دلتان می‌خواهد انجام دهید
من می خواهم از سیاست‌های لینوکس فاصله بگیرم
من می‌خواهم همچون کسی باشم که همه اورا بعنوان پسری خوب قبول دارند و او به کسی نیش نمی‌زند (کنایه به اذیت کردن)
-میشه سوال آخر رو بپرسم؟
-بله حتما!
-من اهل هند هستم.
آیا شما کمک‌های زیادی از توسعه‌دهندگان هندی برای توسعه کرنل دریافت کردید؟
نه خیلی.
شما چه پیامی برای آن‌ها دارید تا که شاید کمک‌های بیشتری از آن‌ها دریافت کنید؟
من فکر می‌کنم این یک مشکل زیرساختی‌ است.
آن‌ها لزوما به اینترنت دسترسی ندارند یا سرعت اینترنتشان بسیار ضعیف است.
من فکر می‌کنم مردمشان برای انجام همکاری از اینترنت استفاده نمی‌کنند.
آن‌ها به گونه‌های مختلفی عصبی هستند، درسته؟
چه پیامی دارید برای آنکه به بیشتر شدن توسعه‌دهندگانشان انگیزه دهید؟
من نمی‌دونم چه مسائلی در هند وجود دارد، اما به سمت مسأله‌دار شدن می‌روند.
-مثل این مسأله عمومی که مردم هند می‌خواهند بتوانند هرکاری انجام دهند
-که قارهٔ امریکا برای همه اهمیت قائل نمی‌شود.
و من فکر می‌کنم واقعا خیلی انگیزه بخش است وقتی کسی می‌گوید:
-"هی، من می‌توانم این مشکل را حل کنم، و لینوکس خودم را توسعه دهم"
-"و این برای من بعنوان یک هندی و یا هرکسی بسیار بهتر خواهد بود".
And that's how you should be motivated,
and whatever I say you should not care!
Thank you very much!
-You come down to India next time...
-I will try to...
Do you want to take a
picture for a Dutch magazine?
Are you planning on
coming to the Netherlands?
The real value of Linux may be some-
where else than knocking Microsoft out.
Linux was designed to run on a cheap
hardware and to solve common problems.
If you are poor it is a
real alternative, free of charge.
The Linux project started
in Europe and the United States.
But now, free software
allows it to find ever more-
-new programmers
from new sources-
-from regions where
computing is still in its infancy.
Beijing, China
China is behind the developed
countries in the IT industry.
The gap is big and
we try to catch up as fast we can.
During this we have to borrow
from other countries' experiences.
We put a great importance
on the operating system.
We did some
development work based on UNIX-
Due to tight market control
we were not able to succeed.
Linux provides us
with a very good opportunity
-and a base to learn
from advanced technology.
"The Chinese Red Army
delighted with Linux"
I think that this is the greatest
transfer of wealth we may have ever seen-
-between the industrialized
rich north, and put Europe and-
-the United States together
in that, and the third world!
It's the open source.
I think this is
important to many people.
I like philosophy, and I like to analyze
matters from a philosophic perspective.
The open source is in
accordance with the spirit of science-
-the free and unrestricted
access to information.
Nothing should be hidden.
That's my first impression of Linux.
The spirit could be
expanded to other fields.
I never feel that this
only applies in the computer field.
You have one of the most privileged
classes in capitalism: programmers!
They can make so much
money from working as programmers-
-that they have the time
to devote to their own hobbies.
Programmers like Alan Cox,
they could name their price!
Here are these people who
are at the top of the heap, and through-
-the structure of transfer of intellectual
property they've come up with,-
-they're transferring that wealth.
It is socialism in action,
even if the libertarians-
-are horrified
whenever that is mentioned.
Open source projects have been
compared to the way science is created.
Science in itself
doesn't make money-
The wealth comes as
the result of applications.
For the open source
hackers developing Linux-
-has traditionally been a science-
like voluntary project. A hobby.
Eventually, the best
Linux hackers were enlisted.
In 1999, during the dot-com boom,
some of the Linux companies went public.
Wall Street announced record-
breaking value for Linux stock.
Of course it didn't last,
but for a period of time-
-some Linux hackers
were filthy rich - on paper.
Just about everyone who
was a core developer before-
-all this whoopla about people
making money doing Linux-
-have kept to their
values in taking these jobs.
Most of the ones I keep in contact with,
have a very crucial position and are-
-pretty much doing all of the Linux work
they were doing before they had the job-
-with the same levels of freedom, as well.
I still got changes from people every day-
-I still submitted them to Linus, the
same way I always did before the IPO.
Some of us are driving nicer cars than
beforehand. That's the only difference.
Maybe we're eating
a little bit more sushi.
There are some people who got lucky,
joined the right company at the right time.
Managed to participate in the IPO
lottery and there are some people who-
-got millions of dollars, and there are
some people who got billions of dollars!
Did those people actually contribute more
to the company than those other people?
In some cases they just
happened to contribute the right-
-amount of investment
money at the right time.
I think that's a generic problem that's
not unique to the open source community.
I don't know if we actually
have a good solution for that.
Part of what I like about
Silicon Valley is just that it's so dynamic,-
-and you can do anything here.
And even the money-grabbing
approach. Even if it's slightly tasteless-
-especially when you come from Europe,
it's a really good motivational factor.
It's a really good way
of getting things done.
Has it changed me?
I assume so.
I'm not the same
person I was when I moved-
-but I don't think it's made me all that
more money-conscious than I used to be.
2001 - Imagined by Stanley Kubrick.
In the most ambitious and
grotesque PR stunt in history-
-suicide hijackers blitz America
with far-reaching consequences.
IT recession
affects also open source.
No longer does Linus have to act
in public all the time as an enlightened-
-philosopher ruler, harassed by the media.
With the coolness of Linux still intact-
-the phenomenon
disappears into gadgets.
Invisible pieces of technology for
households and entertainment industry.
Gradually, many of us turn into
Linux users when the code infiltrates-
-our clocks, toasters
and mobile phones.
As for bigger ideals, it could be one of the
greatest missed opportunities of our times-
-if free software
liberated nothing but code.
There's no question that
development of technology-
-is just going to make
Linux obsolete at some point.
The question is just:
"How long will it take?"
Will it be in 5 years, or
15 years or will it be 50 years?
I think one of the powers of
open source is that in 50 years-
-the next operating system
that's the best at the time-
-will be able to take advantage
of the source base that Linux had.
The source code itself is
going to be the memory of Linux-
-and people can always
use that as a kind of blueprint.
But there's more in that.
There's also the intangible issues-
-about why things
were designed a certain way.
I think those are out
there even if I weren't out there...
The Code - Story of Linux ©2001